<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<?rfc private="yeti-template"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced.
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2826 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2826.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8324 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8324.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8483 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8483.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7626 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7626.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.boneh-bls-signature SYSTEM
    "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-boneh-bls-signature-00.xml">
<!--  <!ENTITY I-D.ihren-dnsext-threshold-validation SYSTEM
    "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ihren-dnsext-threshold-validation-01.xml"> -->

]>
<!--<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>-->
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<!--<?rfc strict="yes" ?>-->
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc docName="draft-yeti-fault-tolerent-root-arch-00">

  <front>

    <title>Fault-tolerant Root High Level Technical Architecture</title>

    <author fullname="Linjian Song" initials="L." surname="Song">
      <organization>Beijing Internet Institute</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2nd Floor, Building 5, No.58 Jing Hai Wu Lu, BDA</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>100176</code>
          <country>P. R. China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>songlinjian@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    

    <date/>
    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <!--<area>Internet Area</area>-->
    <workgroup>Yeti Design Team</workgroup>

    <!-- <keyword>dns</keyword> -->

    <abstract>
      <t>
      This document describes the proposed architecture of Fault-tolerant Root 
      for Yeti DNS.  It results from ongoing discussions during the launch of  
      phase-2 for Yeti DNS Project towards a decentralized Root system. This 
      design intends to introduce the property of Fault-tolerance with redundancy 
      and decentralized technology into the signing and publication function of 
      Root. Note that it is only high-level description of the design. Details 
      are to be contained in accompanying documentation.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
      The Internet’s Domain Name System(DNS) is a vital component of Internet 
      infrastructure mapping human-readable names into Internet Protocol (IP) 
      addresses. DNS is designed and built on a single root, known as the Root 
      Server System with editorial function, signing function and publication 
      Function of Root zone. </t>

      <t>
      As part of IANA function, DNS Root zone management has a long history<xref target="SAC067"/> 
      and experienced technical changes (IPv6, DNSSEC, Anycast etc) as well as policy 
      changes (IANA transition, new gTLD). None of previous changes violates the 
      assumption that a centralized entity responsible for one particular function 
      in the Root zone management. For example, IANA takes the role of editorial 
      and Key Signing functions. VeriSign takes the role of Zone 
      signing and publication function which distributes the root zone to 13 
      root servers and their instances. This centralized design fits the need to keep 
      a single, globally Unique DNS Root <xref target="RFC2826"/> </t>

      <t>
      Recent years as the rise of DNS privacy <xref target="RFC7626"/>, high resiliency and 
      Internet policy concerns on Internet infrastructure, thoughts of introducing 
      fault-tolerance and decentralization technology into DNS are getting popular. Some 
      people suggest that "if we were designing a next-generation DNS using today's 
      technology, it should be possible to remove the technical requirement for a 
      central authority over the root" <xref target="RFC8324"/>. Yeti DNS Testbed 
      <xref target="RFC8483"/> proposed and built a model introducing three ZSK 
      signers and root zone distributors. Yeti's model shows a form of root 
      "democracy" governance but it is not fault-tolerant and scalable enough 
      technically speaking <xref target="FDMA"/>. It gives us motivation to 
      upgrade Yeti Root to "higher" level by introducing the properties of 
      decentralization and fault-tolerance.
      </t>

      <t>
      This document describes the proposed architecture of Fault-tolerant Root 
      for Yeti DNS. It results from ongoing discussions during the launch of 
      phase-2 for Yeti DNS Project towards a decentralized Root system. It firstly 
      reviews the state of art including how IANA and Yeti Root works, as well as 
      some previous proposals in this field. It proposes to introduce Threshold 
      Signing cryptographic technology to bring redundancy for Yeti Root DNSSEC. 
      It also introduces a layer of DM network with consensus algorithm to keep 
      the consistency of Root zone and meta data.</t>

      <t>
      Note that it is only high-level description of the design. Details of some modules 
      are to be contained in accompanying documentation.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Background and Motivation">

    <section title="Breif Review of IANA Root" anchor="IANA_ROOT">

    <t>
      According to <xref target="SAC067"/> , the components of IANA Root 
      involves four independent parties after IANA Transition: 1) the change 
      requester, usually the manager(s) or administrator(s) of the TLD; 
      2) ICANN/PTI, as the IANA Functions Operator;3) VeriSign, as the 
      Root Zone Maintainer(RZM); and 4) the Root Server Operators. Their 
      relationship and data flow among them are shown in figure 1 below.
    </t>

      <figure anchor="components" title="Root zone update process and data flow">
        <artwork>
          <![CDATA[
                 +----------------+
                 |  TLD operators |
                 +-----+----+-----+
                       |    |
            DS records |    |Change requests
                       v    v
                 +-----+----+-----+
                 |  IANA operator |
                 +-----+----+-----+
                       ^    |
            Key Signing|    | updated Root zone
                       v    v
                 +-----+----+-----+
                 |   Root Zone    |
                 | Maintainer(RZM)|
                 +-------+--------+
                         |
                         | Notify and zone transfer
                         v
                +-+ +-+ +++       +-+
                |A| |B| |C| + + + |M|
                +-+ +-+ +-+       +-+
]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        There are two important roles in the figure: IANA operator 
        and Root zone maintainer(RZM). They are the centralized roles in 
        the whole process regarding root zone editorial, signing and 
        publication functions.
      </t>

      <t>
        ICANN/PTI as the IANA operator is the interface to TLD operators 
        and is responsible to collect root zone change requests and to vet 
        and process DS records sent from TLD operator. ICANN/PTI is also 
        responsible for management of root zone KSK, including generation, 
        publication, and use for signing in cooperation with the Internet 
        community according to <xref target="DNSSEC-Root"/>.
      </t>

      <t>
        VeriSign as the Root zone Maintainer(RZM) is responsible for incorporating 
        DNSSEC-related changes into the root zone file, signing the file with the 
        ZSK, and distribute the signed root zone file to the root servers. It is also 
        referred as to Distribution Master (DM). RZM and DM are both used in following 
        sessions as the role of signing and publishing root zone. Note that there is 
        an exchange of ZSK and Signed DNSKEY set between IANA operator and RZM.  
      </t>

      <t>
        In Yeti Root, the role of VeriSign is replaced by three DMs who pull the 
        unsigned zone from IANA, sign it with their ZSK and distribute the root 
        zone among 25 root server independently. This approach 
        introduces certain redundancy using current DNS technology.  
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Previous Proposals and discussions" anchor="related-work">
      <t>
      When it refers to decentralization technology, Blockchain comes to 
      people's mind which is a buzzle word recent years. Based on Blockchain, 
      there are some naming service systems like ENS (https://ens.domains/ ) 
      in Ethereum network and Namecoin (https://namecoin.org/) in Bitcoin netowrk. 
      They introduce .eth and .bit respectively as special TLDs used only in their 
      overlay network as well as special registration and resolution protocols. 
      They are not DNS, but referred to as Blockchain-based DNS in literatures though.
      </t>

      <t>
        In Yeti DNS Project, from the beginning, we keep boundaries for One 
        Unique Internet Identifier and not amending the IANA name space. However, 
        the Blockchain-based DNS does not fit DNS in operation network. 
        They have different name space and use different resolving protocols. 
        As introduced in <xref target="components"/>, the Root system is decoupled 
        into three functions: editing, signing and publication. It is possible to keep 
        the root zone intact and make changes to signing and publication functions 
        to meet our requirement. 
      </t>

      <t>
        There are some approaches introduce alternative method to access the unique 
        name space. Loopback Root <xref target="RFC8483"/>is one 
        alternative root zone publication approach in which the signed root zone 
        is replicated in resolver. Changes are made only in publication function.</t> 
      
      <t>
        Yeti DNS <xref target="RFC8483"/> is one example made changes in both signing 
        and publication functions. Yeti root zone is signed by three DMs and 
        distributed the root zone to a different set of root servers. Yeti Multi-DM 
        model makes change to signing function (Zone Signing), but current version 
        of Multi-DM does not scale due to increased DNS response by introducing 
        multiple ZSKs.
       </t>

       <t>
        On Root signing function, John Ihren and Bill manning [draft-ihren-dnsext-threshold-validation] once proposed a mechanism called threshold validation to improved trust and redundancy 
        for DNSSEC Keys. Basically it require resolvers to validate multiple 
        signatures signed by multiple trust entities. If the number of successful 
        validation reaches a threshold, then the outcome of multiple validations 
        as a whole is VALID. Similar with Yeti model, it does not scale given 
        the limitation of DNS packet size (contain multiple KEY and signature). 
        It also require changes on every validating resolver which make it a task 
        impossible.
       </t>

       <t>Is it possible to introduce multiple independent Signers without 
        changing the DNSSEC validation interface, and without augmenting the 
        size of DNS response as well? The work of NIC Chile on "Distributed 
        Threshold Cryptography"<xref target="Threshold-Chile"/> gives a clue which was 
        introduced in 2019 Yeti workshop in Tokyo. With Threshold Cryptography 
        scheme, it is possible to aggregate all types of primitives (secret keys, 
        public keys, signatures) and the result is always another valid primitive 
        to fit the interface of PKCS#11 [PKCS11]. However, there is still a centralized roll 
        called SD (Signing Dealer) in charge of distributing zone file, collecting 
        and aggregating the signatures for each update of root zone.
       </t>
    </section>

   </section>

    <section title= "Framework of Fault-tolerant Root" anchor="Framework">

    <section title="Hypotheses and Goal" anchor="GOAL_Requirement">
      
      <t>
        To design a distributed system which does not rely upon one entity, 
        there should be some hypotheses of the participants to limit the scope 
        of risk. There is one notable assumption that all participants of the 
        fault-tolerant root designed in this draft are cooperative and with 
        no malicious intention. It means that the system is design against 
        technical failures like data inconsistency, single point of failure, etc. 
        It can be achieved by adopting a selective and invitation-based strategy 
        to choose a group of participants with credit. It is similar to the 
        concept of permission chain in Blockchain context. 
      </t>

      <t>
        Based on the related work and the hypotheses, the goal and technical 
        requirement of desirable fault-tolerant root is listed as follows:   
      </t>

      <t>
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>To introduce redundancy and fault-tolerance property on both signing 
          and publication functions in case of single point failure.
        </t>
        <t>To provide consistency check on to-be published root zone in 
          case of date inconsistency in a distributed manner.
        </t>
        <t>
          New proposed scheme SHOULD be deployed on authority server only 
          which means no change is required on recursive server. Chile NIC's 
          proposal as a kind of PKCS#11 provider is a good starting pint.
        </t>
        <t>
          New proposed scheme SHOULD not be introducing huge increase 
          (>1200 octets) on the size of DNS response.
        </t>
      </list>
       </t>
      </section>

      <section title= "Roles and Responsibilities">

      <figure anchor="Framework_root" title="The framework in Fault-tolerant Root">
        <artwork>
          <![CDATA[        
       +---------------+    +---------------+
       | KeyGen Dealer |    | TLD Operators |
       +---------------+    +---------------+
               |                    | TLD Zone Changes
               |Key Share           | (NS, KSK, glue)
               |                    |
   +-----------v----------------- --v------------+
   |                                             |
   |     +--------+      +--------+              |
   |     |Yeti DM1|      |Yeti DM2|      + + +   |
   |     +--------+      +--------+              |
   |         |                |                  |
   |   +-------------------------------------+   |
   |               |                  |          |
   |           +--------+         +--------+     |
   |           |Yeti DM3|         |Yeti DM4|     |
   |           +--------+         +--------+     |
   |                                             |
   | Yeti DM network                             |
   +---------------------------------------------+
                          |
                          | Root Zone Publication
                          v
    +-+   +-+   +-+   +-+   +-+   +-+         +--+
    |1|   |2|   |3|   |4|   |5|   |6|  + + +  |25|
    +-+   +-+   +-+   +-+   +-+   +-+         +--+

]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>

        <t>
          The framework in fault-tolerant root is shown in Figure 2. There are 
          several roles are similar to ones in Figure 1 like TLD Operators and 
          Root servers. The difference in the interaction with TLD Operators 
          is that in figure 1 TLD operators can push zone change request and 
          DS to ICANN/PTI. But in Yeti, it is to pull the data and generate 
          DS record locally. From the TLD data point of view, they are mostly 
          identical except some NS records are present in TLD zone but not 
          in root zone. 
        </t>

        <t>
        Different from a single RZM in IANA root, there is a group of Yeti DM 
        (>= 3) who are fully connected as a cluster and form a Yeti 
        DM network. The Yeti DM network take the role of signing and publishing 
        Root zone acting as one DM with the assistance of two key components : 
        threshold signing and consensus algorithm. It is a desirable capability 
        that failure on small parts of Yeti DM network (a threshold number of DMs) 
        will not be able to take down the whole system. Note that the numbers of DM 
        and threshold are testing targets helping us to understand the limit 
        of the system.
        </t>

      <t>
        There is a special role in Figure 2 is the KeyGen Dealer who is 
        responsible to generate the keys (or key shares) to each yeti DM.
        Special secret sharing algorithm is used to generate keys with 
        property of threshold. In <xref target="threshold-signing"/>, there is a 
        introduction of threshold signing which will help readers to 
        understand the basic primitives and process. Note that this document does 
        not dive into specific threshold signing algorithm and protocol. Instead 
        related data flow and function interface will be introduced. 
      </t>

      </section>
      <section title= "The Data Flow and Process">

       <t>
      In Figure 3, there is a chart of data flow and process as a routine 
      for Yeti root zone update from one Yeti DM's point of view.
    </t>

    <t>Basically as an input each Yeti DM periodically pull the TLD data 
      information (KSK, NS, glue) from each TLD authoritative servers. 
      As a sequence there are 5 steps:0) Key Generation , 1) generate 
      unsigned root zone, 2) Sign the zone with the key shares, 3) generate 
      Signed Root zone with consensus among all Yeti DM, 4) Publish the 
      signed Root zone file to Yeti root servers. 
    </t>

       <t>
      Note that steps 1), 2) and 3) require Yeti DMs to coordinate and act as 
      an "One DM". That means in each step, each Yeti DM should broadcast 
      the values or root zone, signature, Signed root zone to others until 
      final consensus on that values are reached. In <xref target="Consensus"/>, 
      there is a introduction of consensus algorithm which will help readers to
      understand the basic property and interaction between Yeti DMs. Note that 
      we will not dive into specific consensus algorithm in this draft. 
    </t>

      <figure anchor="Data_flow_process" title="The Data Flow and Process">
        <artwork>
          <![CDATA[
                           +
                           |  Root Zone
                           |  Information
                           |
              +------------|-------------+
              |   Yeti DM  |             |
              |  +---------v----------+  |
              |  |1.Generate unsigned |  |
              |  |  Root zone         |<--------------+
              |  +---------+----------+  |            |
              |            |             |     +------v----+
+------+      |  +---------v----------+  |     |           |
|Dealer|+-----> +2.Threshold Signing  |<------>|           |
+------+      |  |   and Aggregation  |  |     | Yeti DM   |
     0.KeyGen |  +---------+----------+  |     | Consensus |
              |            |             |     | Network  <-----> 
              |  +---------v----------+  |     |           |with other
              |  |3.Generate Signed   |<------>|           |Yeti DM
              |  |  Root zone file    |  |     |           |
              |  +---------+----------+  |     +-----------+
              |            |             |           
              |  +---------v----------+  |           
              |  |4.Publish the signed|  |           
              |  |  Root zone file    |  |
              |  +---------+----------+  |
              +------------+-------------+
                           |
                           | Notify and zone transfer
                           v
                  +-+ +-+ +++       +--+
                  |1| |2| |3| + + + |25|
                  +-+ +-+ +-+       +--+

]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>

    
    <t>In the following subsections each step will be discuss briefly. They focus 
      on "what to do" other than "how to do". More detailed how-to-do specification 
      is to be defined in next version or in other documentation.
    </t>

      <section title= "Step 0: Key Generation">
        <t>
          A Key Generation process (KeyGen for short) is required in the beginning 
          of Yeti Root system setup. It can be a centralized process with a group 
          of people and broadcast globally via a auditable process like a IANA KSK 
          ceremony (https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/presentation-root-ksk-protection-key-ceremonies-13may17-en.pdf) 
        </t>

        <t>
          In the context Fault-tolerant Root, The KeyGen process has at least two 
          outcomes: 1) KSK shares for each Yeti DM, 2) ZSK shares for each Yeti DM. 
          Different from IANA Key Ceremony, Key Signing process is done by each Yeti 
          DM independently. Secret KSK and ZSK is no need to be maintained and kept 
          safe in a special device because they are not required in the following process. 
          They can be destroyed after KeyGen is done or kept for emergency purpose. 
        </t>

        <t>
          Note that the KeyGen dealer in figure 2 and 3 is more light-weighted than 
          the Signing Dealer in NIC Chile's proposal, but it is still a centralized 
          role involving human activities in the system. It is technical possible to 
          further remove the KeyGen dealer role by deploying a certain Distributed Key 
          Generation (DKG) method (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Distributed_key_generation). 
        </t>

      </section>
          <section title= "Step 1: Generate unsigned Root zone">
        
        <t>
          According to RFC8483, the Yeti unsigned root zone is composed of two part : APEX 
          records of Root and the TLD data. APEX data can be specified in the beginning. 
          (To Be Defined for SOA, NS and DNSKEY respectively)</t>
        <t>
          TLD data includes DS record, NS RRset and glue of a particular TLD. 
          Periodically TLD data is pulled from authority servers of each TLD. 
          The authority list of TLD is from IANA website (www.iana.org/domains/root/db).
          Note that DS record of each TLD can be generated using their KSK information.
          More specifically </t>

          <t>It is worth mentioning that Each Yeti DM will pull the data independently 
            and save them as a &lt;key,value&gt; pair. More specifically the &lt;name, 
            type, class&gt; is the key, and &lt;TTL, RRset&gt; is the value. Each one 
            of the values are considered as to-be-confirm state until all Yeti DMs 
            agree on the values via the consensus network running consensus protocol. 
            If every Yeti DM follows the same procedure as a protocol, the confirmed 
            unsigned root zone will be formed finally.  
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title= "Step 2: Threshold Signing and and Aggregation">
        <t>Each Yeti DM will use the key share to sign the zone delivering RRSIG for 
          each RRset. The RRSIG of each RRset per Yeti DM (with DM ID) will be broadcast 
          via Yeti DM consensus network. Finally each Yeti DM will connect all RRSIG records
          signed by all Yeti DMs which is confirmed via the consensus network. 
        </t>

        <t>
          With all RRSIG records, Yeti DM can aggregate them into one RRSIG record using 
          Aggregation function. In Threshold Signing scheme, if the number of failures of 
          DM signing is less than threshold t, the system will survive by aggregating a 
          signature which will output VAILD validated against the Public Key.
        </t>
      </section>      
      <section title= "Step 3: Generate Signed Root zone">
        <t>
          For each RRset, a aggregated RRSIG is generated locally by each Yeti DM. 
          All aggregated RRSIGs are to be confirmed via consensus network. After 
          confirmation, A Signed Root zone will be generated without inconsistency.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title= "Step 4: Publish the Signed Root zone">
        <t>
          Yeti DM will send notify to all root servers. Root server will configure 
          its Zone transfer ACl with invited Yeti DM. It is possible that a root 
          server receive more than on notify in a short period. Only the first notify 
          carrying the new serial of SOA will trigger the zone transfer request.  
        </t>

        <t>It is possible to configure a smaller mapping of DMs and Root servers to 
          reduce the notify storm. For example, one DM only notify 5 root servers and 
          3 DM are configure in each root server's ACL. 
        </t>
      </section>
  </section>
    </section>


    <section title= "Security considerations">

      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">

    <t>No IANA considerations for this memo</t>

    </section>

   <section title="Acknowledgments">

    <t>
    Special thanks for NIC Chile's work on Distributed Threshold Cryptography 
    which inspires this draft.
    </t>
  </section> <!-- Acknowledgments -->
  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="References">
      &RFC8483;&RFC2826;&RFC8324;&RFC7626;&I-D.boneh-bls-signature;<!-- &I-D.ihren-dnsext-threshold-validation; -->
     <reference anchor="FDMA" target="https://yeti-dns.org/yeti/blog/2018/08/13/fault-tolerant-distribution-master-architecture.html">
            <front>
                <title>Fault-tolerant Distribution Master Architecture</title>
                <author fullname="Linjian Song" initials="L." surname="SONG"/>
                <date year="2018" month="August" day="18"/>
            </front>
     </reference>  

          <reference anchor="SAC067" target="https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/sac-067-en.pdf">
            <front>
                <title>Overview and History of the IANA Functions</title>
                <author>
                </author>
                <date year="2014" month="August" day="15"/>
            </front>
     </reference>  
          <reference anchor="DNSSEC-Root" target="http://www.root-dnssec.org/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/draft-icann-dnssec-arch-v1dot4.pdf">
            <front>
                <title>DNSSEC Root Zone High Level Technical Architecture</title>
                <author>
                </author>
                <date year="2010" month="June" day="7"/>
            </front>
     </reference>  
      
      <reference anchor="Threshold-Chile" target="http://yeti-dns.org/resource/2019-3-2/threshold-crypto-4-root-hsalgado.pdf">
            <front>
                <title>Distributed Threshold cryptography: a novel way to distribute keys and signing for DNSSEC</title>
                <author fullname="Hugo Salgado" initials="H." surname="Salgado"/>
                <date year="2019" month="March" day="2"/>
            </front>
     </reference>       
     </references>

   <section title= "Basic componets and operation of Threshold Signing" anchor="threshold-signing">
    <t>
      Before introducing new design of Yeti Root, it is necessary to briefly 
      introduce the property of Threshold Signing with basic primitives and 
      operation which is the key components of the fault-tolerant root. 
    </t>
    
    <t> Generally speaking, threshold signing require two crypto components:   
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>The first component is a key generation process with secret sharing 
          scheme which generates multiple secret key shares from the secret key. 
          Secret sharing system is also called a (t,n)-threshold scheme 
          due to the property that a number (number >= t) of secret shares can 
          reconstruct the secret to be used to sign. However, secret sharing 
          scheme itself require a dealer to recover the original secret key 
          which is also possible to be stolen and compromised during that period. 
          To avoid the risk, a special signature scheme is need as the second component. 
        </t>

        <t>A signature scheme with the property of primitives aggregation is the 
          second key component. With that signature scheme all types of primitives 
          like secret keys, public keys, signatures can be aggregated, and the 
          result is always another valid primitive. The secret key shares generated in 
          the first component are also valid secret keys which can be used to sign a 
          message and thus create a valid signature. The dealer or anyone can take 
          t-of-n of these signature shares to recover a new signature which is 
          identical to what would have been created if the original secret key would 
          have been used. So the secret key would never appear or be observed after 
          key generate process. (BLS Signature Scheme <xref target="I-D.boneh-bls-signature"/>
          is one example of aggregatable signature scheme)
        </t>
        </list>
    </t>

    <t>
      Based on the components of threshold signing, there are several operations 
      provided to fulfill the threshold signing process
    </t>

    <t>
    <list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
     <t hangText="KeyGen:"> Given the key_pair (public key and secret key), the 
      number of authorities (n) and the threshold (t), KeyGen operation can 
      generate a group of secret key shares (sks_group) by performing 
      KeyGen(key_pair, t, n) which outputs sks_group </t>

      <t hangText="Sign:"> For each secret key share (sks), it can be used to 
        sign the message (msg) to generate a signature share (sigma) by performing 
        Sign(sk, msg) which outputs sigma. Note that a group of secret key share (sks_group) 
        can generate a group of signatures share (sigma_group) </t>

      <t hangText="Aggregate_sigma:"> Given any t out of n signatures share signed by 
        secret key shares, an aggregated signature can be generated by performing 
        Aggregate_sigma(sigma_1, ... sigma_t) which output VALID and sigma_aggregated. 
        However if Aggregate_sigma failed and outputs not aggregated signature, it means 
        there is not enough (less then t) valid signature shares are collected. This operation 
        is a key design introducing (n-t) redundancy which means if no more than (n-t+1) 
        keys was compromised, the system will not be taken down. (To Be Confirmed and doble checked with crypto scholar)</t>
      <t hangText="Verify:"> The Verify operation is the same as other signing and validating 
        process, by perform Verify(PK, msg, sigma_aggregated) outputs VALID if not error here.</t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    Note that there is a still a centralized dealer to generate key and key shares and 
    distributed to n players but just in the beginning. The threshold signing described 
    above require not dealer in each update of msg. In the context of root, after key 
    generation process (like a Key ceremony), all process of root zone signing and 
    publication can be done in a distributed and automatic manner.  
  </t>

   </section>
    <section title= "Consensus algorithm" anchor="Consensus">

      <t>
        It is quoted that consensus is a fundamental problem in fault-tolerant 
        distributed systems. Consensus involves multiple servers agreeing on values. 
        Once they reach a decision on a value, that decision is final. In this 
        section, there is a brief introduction of Raft consensus algorithm 
        (https://raft.github.io/) as a background.
      </t>

    <t>
      TBD
    </t>
   </section>
  </back>
</rfc>

